♪ [MUSIC] ♪
CORDOVA: Please...
CORDOVA: Pick up your wallet.
CORDOVA: Please don't ignore it.
KATHERINE: What's in your suitcase?
DETAINEE: Well, we discovered that it contains drugs...
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: Jorge Chávez International Airport,
in Lima, Peru.
39 percent of passengers traveling on this route
Busy air terminal boards international flights.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
There are almost 10 thousand people who use the 54 counters daily.
open 24 hours a day to carry out check-in procedures.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
Now it is the turn of a plane that will travel to Spain,
a destination classified as hot by the police
anti-drug, as it could be a potentially point
attractive to drug trafficking networks.
Surveillance is rigorous and agents warn
strange behavior in one of the passengers who make
your check-in procedures.
GUARDAMINO: Good afternoon, sir,
Please allow me your passport.
SUSPECT: Yes, ma'am.
GUARDAMINO: its final destination?
SUSPECT: Barcelona.
GUARDAMINO: Reason for your trip?
SUSPECT: I have several reasons.
GUARDAMINO: But for tourism or work?
SUSPECT: Work, tourism. GUARD: For work.
At the time he checks in, I go myself.
and I intervene, I ask him a series of questions where he was
a little nervous, he laughed alone, looked around,
a person who seemed a little suspicious to me.
First time traveling there or is it already the second...
SUSPECT: No, I've already lived,
I have lived in Barcelona for 15 years.
GUARDAMINO: You have lived there.
We're going to do a little inspection of your suitcase.
of airplane luggage, yes?
Could you please accompany me?
SUSPECT: Yes.
NARRATOR: Once transferred to the inspection room,
The passenger seems increasingly restless and although the agents
They have only asked you to perform a routine check-up on your
luggage, something unexpected happens that increases suspicions.
GUARDAMINO: Is everything you carry in your suitcase yours?
Or do you carry out orders, commissions?
GUARDAMINO: It's yours.
You packed your suitcase yourself.
SUSPECT: Yes.
GUARDIAN: Do you have your key, please?
It should be here.
GUARDAMINO: When asking for the key to open
the suitcase because it had a padlock,
He said that his key had been lost,
I couldn't find the key, it seemed strange.
NARRATOR: In these cases, given the presumption that the person
would be obstructing the inspection,
Local law authorizes the police to act by forcing the lock
or using a master key.
GUARDAMINO: I have a key here, it's already opened.
It's not yours, it's mine.
GUARD: Put on gloves.
GUARDAMINO: Where did you buy this?
GUARDAMINO: How many are you carrying?
GUARDAMINO: At the moment the suitcase was opened we found the
surprise that he was carrying handmade rugs that normally
Well, a tourist or a traveler takes it.
He carried more than a dozen of those mats.
Did you buy it yourself?
SUSPECT: Yes.
Safe?
SUSPECT: Yes, yes.
GUARDAMINO: Or was it handed over to him?
Give me the awl, awl, that little black guy, please.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
Turquoise blue, when the, the, this here paints what it is
turquoise blue, it is indicative of drugs.
Indicative for drug.
Sir, you are under arrest by the Peruvian police, yes, sir?
SUSPECT: Yes, miss.
GUARDAMINO: Just leave everything there, sir, okay?
Leave all your stuff there, okay?
You can't do anything anymore, okay?
You just stand there just like you are, okay?
Turn around please.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
Positive, already?
OFFICER: Sir?
GUARDAMINO: Who accompanied you to the airport?
GUARDAMINO: Sure?
SUSPECT: Yes.
GUARDAMINO: We will visualize it anyway
for the cameras, right?
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: The next flight to Mexico is being prepared
to leave, and in the lobby, the police have few
minutes to observe the passengers and detect possible
burriers or drug dealers.
Now they notice a young student who claims to have done
tourism for 5 days.
NARRATOR: So far, the young man's answers indicate
who could actually be a tourist,
However, officers need to be fully
sure that he is telling the truth, and continue the interrogation.
NARRATOR: The officers detect inconsistencies in the story.
of the young man and suspect that the excuse of tourism,
It could be a front for illegal activity.
AZURIN: In the interview we noticed some inconsistencies,
some inconsistencies in their answers.
We noticed that the passport was also very new,
He said he had come for tourism.
And when he mentions that he had only been there for a day
In Cusco, he gave us some indication to proceed.
to the inspection of your luggage.
You tell me this is your first time visiting Peru, right?
AZURIN: I have a question for you, but it's awkward,
but I have to do it for you.
AZURIN: Are you carrying anything illegal in your suitcase?
-No.
Are you carrying anything illegal in any other way, in any other way?
You don't wear.
OK.
AZURIN: Yes. OK.
NARRATOR: The young man seems confident in his answers.
and collaborates by providing the information they request
the officers.
But when they begin to review the structure
from her handbag, changes her attitude.
[BACKGROUND VOICES]
♪ [MUSIC] ♪ [SPEAKERS]
NARRATOR: The police don't find anything in the handbag.
nothing illegal.
However, there is a detail among the young man's belongings.
that catches their attention.
AZURIN: A person buys a cell phone for only 4 days
arouses in us a little suspicion.
We believe that he does this to communicate with the
organizations that exist here in Peru or in Lima to transport
illicit drugs.
NARRATOR: Now the officers notice something strange on the wall.
from the suitcase and suspect that it could be a double
bottom.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
...positive for cocaine alkaloid...
[RADIO DIALOGS]
NARRATOR: A passenger who intended to fly to Barcelona
He was arrested by the anti-drug police.
The agents discovered that several handmade rugs that
supposedly brought as gifts in reality
They were a device to hide cocaine.
GUARDAMINO: Turquoise blue.
It is indicative of drugs...
NARRATOR: The procedure must continue in the offices
of the Anti-Drug Directorate in the presence of the prosecutor on duty.
Here the behavior of the captured person begins to be disconcerting.
His nervousness seems to have disappeared and not only
He appears serene, and he also dares to assume with sarcasm the difficult
situation that you are going through.
GUARDAMINO: He only has illegal things in his suitcase.
He has not ingested anything.
GUARDAMINO: Sure?
GUARDAMINO: Because if he has ingested...
GUARDAMINO: That dissolves and less than an hour, two hours,
sitting here...
...he's not going to tell it anymore.
GUARDAMINO: Is this your first time traveling, transporting?
GUARDAMINO: Illegal things?
GUARDAMINO: There were times when he was completely unfocused.
He laughed, he was a gentleman, well, a bit strange.
NARRATOR: The next step is to extract the entire
of the illegal shipment.
In the first review, the agents had presumed
that the captured man was carrying about a dozen rugs,
but now they warn that there are even more.
GUARDAMINO: How many?
KATHERINE: Twenty handmade rugs.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
We can see how they have been conditioned, can't we?
Between the two covers of the handmade mat,
Bags containing a substance have been found
white powdery.
NARRATOR: Each of the mats contains
the cleverly hidden narcotics.
Amidst the layers made of alpaca fur
Around 30 packages of cocaine were placed
Firmly fixed and secured under pressure,
The wrappers hardly change the thickness of the mat.
and the alteration of the craftsmanship becomes imperceptible
for untrained eyes.
GUARDAMINO: They had made it so similar to a normal mat
that one can buy on the street, was well sewn,
that it was a little difficult to take them apart.
NARRATOR: Finally the number of wrappers obtained
by the police is surprising:
There are 628 packages of cocaine.
I'm going to cry when I'm alone...
NARRATOR: The weigh-in establishes that the total
The seized drug amounts to 5 kilos and 995 grams.
And now the agents expect the detainee to hand him over to them.
data about the organization that hired you to transfer
shipping to Spain.
However, dealing with the captured,
of strange behavior will not be an easy task.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: Jorge Chávez International Airport
It works non-stop 365 days a year.
This generates a monthly energy consumption of more than
of 3 million 200 thousand kilo watts, which is equivalent to charging
about 14 million 600 thousand mobile phones.
Anti-drug police found cocaine hidden in luggage
of a young man who was heading to Mexico.
NARRATOR: Now the police must carry out the seizure.
of the drug and advance the investigation of the case.
...they painted me very easily and very beautifully...
NARRATOR: As police continue the arrest process
The young man's cell phone starts to ring insistently.
[PHONE RINGING]
NARRATOR: The young man claims that the caller is a stranger.
to the crime.
However, the police believe it could be an accomplice.
AZURIN: We saw a message that the suitcase was already checked in.
When asked about this, the young man could not explain it.
We understand that it may be a code,
a way of communicating or telling things
They are fine, the suitcase no longer has any problems,
pass the controls.
NARRATOR: Now the police must recover the drugs that
It is hidden in the suitcase to determine its exact quantity.
NARRATOR: The drug is hidden under a false bottom in
foil-coated packages attached to the wall
from the suitcase by means of glue.
-Nothing but, no....
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: Far from the easy life that was supposedly promised to him
drug traffickers, now the young student faces
a trial for attempting to carry more than 2 kilos of cocaine
to Mexico and could spend a minimum of 8 years in prison.
A passenger trying to fly to Barcelona was arrested
when it was discovered that twenty handmade rugs that he was carrying
They hid cocaine in their luggage.
KATHERINE: What's in your suitcase?
DETAINEE: Well...
uh...
Well, we discovered that it contains drugs.
OFFICIAL: Is this your first time traveling?
DETAINEE: What did I try to do with a thing like that?
Yes, it's the first time.
And it's the first time I've been arrested.
OFFICER: Also.
DETAINEE: Yes.
NARRATOR: When the police proceed to interrogate
the one captured to obtain data on the drug trafficking network
that has connected with it, his attitude changes completely.
GUARDAMINO: Who did you come to the airport with?
GUARDAMINO: Do you know or have information, apart from yourself,
were more people going to travel?
GUARDAMINO: He doesn't know.
GUARDAMINO: You have to try to cooperate.
You have to think about yourself now. Now.
GUARDAMINO: Where...
did you meet that person?
GUARDAMINO: And how much did they offer you, that they were going to pay you?
GUARDAMINO: Twenty thousand euros.
SALDAÑA: The criminal organization, supposedly,
I was going to pay him twenty thousand euros.
For us it is not very credible, but we have detected some
that in recent times, the payment to the burriers has increased
so that they can run the risk of trying to get away with drugs.
NARRATOR: The decision of the captured,
It is firm and for the Anti-Drug Police agents,
There is nothing left but to close the procedure.
The resolution of the case remains in the hands of the local justice system.
For attempting to transport almost 6 kilograms of cocaine
divided into 628 packages, the detainee could receive
a sentence set between 8 and 15 years in prison.
[SIRENS]
In the last 7 years the passenger movement
Jorge Chávez International Airport has increased
83 percent.
This positions him as one of the most important
in the region.
The next international flight of the day will depart to
Madrid, Spain.
The Anti-Drug Police must once again be alert.
In 2016, 15 percent of shipments
of seized narcotics, were traveling to that destination.
And now among the passengers who are doing their check-in procedures,
The agents profile a young tourist of Latvian nationality
who fails to convincingly explain his stay
in Peru.
KATHERINE: At the time that he was operated on, well,
He seemed nervous, tense, and looked everywhere.
He indicated that he had only been in Magdalena, in a hotel.
It is very suspicious for us, reason why every tourist
who comes to Peru, has tourist places like Machu Picchu,
Lake Titicaca...
AZURIN: All of that gives us an indication
or gives us a presumption of something.
KATHERINE: Is it your property?
KATHERINE: When she opened the suitcase she found
clothing in a minimal quantity.
NARRATOR: Although the clothing shortage is calling
The police are attentive, they find nothing illegal
in the contents of the luggage.
However, they do notice something very strange in the structure itself.
from the suitcase.
KATHERINE: We started taking out all the fabrics,
that the cover and back cover were covered,
We could see that there was melted styrofoam.
NARRATOR: Both the front and back covers are filled.
with Styrofoam, an element foreign to the original construction
from the suitcase.
Therefore the agents proceed to carry out the test
field to check if it is hiding any illicit substances.
AZURIN: Gave a turquoise blue coloration which is presumptive
indicative of cocaine alkaloid.
cocaine alkaloid...
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: It's an unusual and complicated day at the terminal.
air cargo at Jorge Chávez Airport.
Two shipments from different companies,
one bound for Miami, United States, and the other for Romania,
have been classified as suspects.
The Anti-Drug Directorate staff is divided into two
equipment to inspect both shipments at the same time.
PATRICIA: Once through the x-ray machine,
We were already sure that it would be contaminated
due to the way the base was covered.
NARRATOR: The agents detach the figures from the base.
and inside they find a rectangular metal package.
Being sealed makes opening more complicated.
than usual.
After making a small incision in the box,
they carry out the field test.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
PATRICIA: At this moment we see that the reaction
It is a snapshot of a turquoise blue, indicative of positive
for cocaine alkaloid.
Positive for cocaine alkaloid...
NARRATOR: As officers work to extract
all of the cocaine, another group of agents is preparing to
examine the second order.
OSCAR: The x-rays showed that there was
a sculpture with the face of the image of Christ.
It looked a little suspicious like a glued-on lid
at the bottom.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪ [BACKGROUND VOICES]
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
KEYLLA: Uh. This sculpture tests positive for alkaloid.
of cocaine.
Positive for cocaine alkaloid.
NARRATOR: Jorge Chávez International Airport,
from Lima, Peru, it owes its name to the Peruvian aviator Jorge Antonio
Chávez Dartnell, who in 1910 became the first
in crossing the Alps in a monoplane,
achieving one of the most important milestones in aviation
world.
The anti-drug police arrested a passenger of nationality
Latvian woman trying to transport cocaine to Spain.
NARRATOR: Once it was confirmed that the suitcase contained alkaloids
of cocaine, the agents transfer the detainee
towards the offices of the anti-drug unit.
While officers complete the arrest procedures,
The passenger appears surprisingly calm.
Suddenly, something makes the passenger change his attitude.
completely.
[PHONE RINGING]
AZURIN: He told us that he had to answer,
that this was good for both us and him.
AZURIN: He was very angry at all times.
about that person.
That he was the person who had gotten him into this,
that he was going to get revenge, we thought it was just an alibi
to be able to disengage or want to get out of the problem
in which he was involved.
NARRATOR: The young man explains that the person calling him is the one who
He handed her the suitcase.
However, without the presence of the prosecutor in charge,
This call cannot be answered.
NARRATOR: Now the agents must recover the entire
of the drugs that are packed in the suitcase.
Both the cover and the back cover are lined with boards
of styrofoam.
Upon removing them, the officers find four bags
black plastic and all contain cocaine.
BRUNO: A sheet, right? Made of rubber.
It's appreciated here, isn't it?
It's covered in sponge, isn't it? Melted,
in order to go unnoticed by the scanner.
NARRATOR: The drug was conditioned to evade
scanner control and field tests,
since the thick layer of styrofoam placed in front
of narcotics forms a barrier that makes it difficult
its detection.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
1 kilo, 978 grams. Cocaine alkaloid.
NARRATOR: After learning the full contents of the drug
that he was carrying, the young Latvian seems to finally understand
who is seriously involved in a serious crime.
For trying to bring almost 2 kilograms of cocaine into Spain
will face a trial in which he may receive
a sentence of up to 15 years in prison.
[RADIO VOICES]
[SIRENS]
Two packages containing works of art were observed
by the anti-drug police at the cargo terminal.
After being examined both shipments showed their true
content.
KEYLLA: This sculpture gives us a positive for alkaloid
of cocaine, cocaine, cocaine...
NARRATOR: The shipment of the sculpture of Christ had as its
destination Romania, inside the box were also found clothes,
religious objects and a letter addressed to a supposed uncle.
KEYLLA: Dear uncle, I'm sending you my present.
Everything that is for a man is for you, man,
and everything that is for women is for you, aunt.
I am also sending you your present for your little one
religious.
NARRATOR: The agents try to cut the sculpture to extract
the drug camouflaged inside.
[Bangs]
PATRICIA: Positive.
AZURÍN: Very positive.
OSCAR: By destroying the sculpture of the face of Jesus Christ
inside there was powdery drug.
On one side, in one part there was wet sawdust,
coupled with seasonings, apparently pepper, right?
Which is used when transporting drugs to divert
or confuse the dogs.
NARRATOR: While they extract the cocaine found inside
of the sculpture of Christ, in the other seized shipment,
Officers manage to extract two packages hidden in the base
of metal.
PATRICIA: The package has also been wrapped with black tape,
to try to go unnoticed.
The substance is currently being introduced
whitish powdery in a plastic bag
so that a weight can be determined later.
They had conditioned it with adhesive tape,
plastic bag and wax paper.
NARRATOR: Between the two shipments, 2 kilos were seized.
and 200 grams of cocaine.
Trying to camouflage drugs in pieces of art is one of
the methods most used by drug traffickers.
In the last year, 19 sculptures and crafts were confiscated.
with narcotics.
[Bangs]
MÉNDEZ: Positive.
AZURIN: Very positive.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
NARRATOR: At Jorge Chávez Airport,
the officers of the customs superintendence
and the anti-drug police control and check passengers
and luggage for each flight about to depart.
OSCAR: We're going to do a routine inspection,
If you could accompany me to the counter, please.
NARRATOR: But sometimes the procedures get complicated.
unexpectedly when some people get upset
with the controls.
THIANA: Good evening, may I see your passport, please?
Anti-drug police.
THIANA: It's a random inspection,
and please could you give me your passport.
THIANA: Could you give me your passport...
Passenger: Who? THIANA: ...please?
THIANA: Please, could you grab your things?
SALDAÑA: The controls we carry out here obey
to a constitutional mandate.
There may be passengers who refuse or have
quite aggressive behavior.
CORDOVA: You have to open the suitcase.
CÓRDOVA: You'll have to accompany us then, ma'am.
CORDOVA: Well, perfect then, now.
THIANA: Please take your things.
THIANA: I'm telling you to give me your passport.
CORDOVA: What's the problem?
THIANA: I have not disrespected him.
SALDAÑA: We have the legal support to do so.
that intervention and to be able to inspect those luggages.
CORDOVA: Ma'am, pick up your purse.
Please...
CORDOVA: ...pick up your wallet.
CORDOVA: Please don't ignore it.
CORDOVA: Okay, let's tell the prosecutor that you are
resisting police intervention.
NARRATOR: Finally the passenger comes to her senses and decides
lend itself to control.
In the body scan room it was confirmed that she was not wearing
nothing illegal.
And he was able to continue his journey.
THIANA: Yeah, BEEP, negative.
Report it to the prosecutor.
That would be all, right?
We'll accompany you to the taxi, okay?
NARRATOR: A young man with a suspicious attitude attracts attention.
of the anti-drug police in the check-in area,
so they proceed to interview him.
JENNIFER: Reason for your trip?
DETAINEE: Mmm... Tourism.
BECERRA: Who bought your ticket?
DETAINEE: Me.
BECERRA: Do you work?
Do you study?
How did you pay for your ticket?
BECERRA: Who gave you the money to buy the ticket?
AZURÍN: What is your uncle's name?
AZURÍN: And he was the one who gave you the money for the ticket?
AZURIN: In the questions that were asked, some were noted
inconsistencies.
The way he responded seemed very suspicious to us.
their behavior.
What boy?
What is his name?
AZURÍN: You don't know.
AZURIN: And why do you mention your uncle?
NARRATOR: The brief interview was enough to confirm
the first suspicions.
The next step will be to check the suitcases to confirm
if he is actually carrying drugs.
SALDAÑA: When inspecting your hold luggage, it is detected
that inside the clothes there were a series of Peruvian products that
was supposedly carrying as souvenirs,
as gifts for their friends.
AZURIN: We are taking various products out of this suitcase.
I want you to be aware of what we are putting out.
I want you to watch this, okay?
We are doing field testing on one of the products
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
and has tested positive for cocaine alkaloid.
positive for cocaine alkaloid...
NARRATOR: It has been operating at the Airport since 1981.
International Jorge Chávez a dependency of the Unit of
Explosive Ordnance Disposal, also known as UDEX.
This unit has a team of 12 highly qualified people
qualified to intervene in the deactivation,
neutralization and destruction of suspicious artifacts
found.
Now, faced with the discovery of an abandoned box in the sector
of counters, the corresponding protocol is initiated.
NARRATOR: The staff clears the area to protect the
passenger safety.
The canine unit is the first to inspect the object.
Not detecting the presence of explosives,
Officers begin the opening and inspection process.
Once the specialist's work is complete,
This determined that it was a false alarm.
The explosive ordnance disposal unit intervenes
3 to 5 items daily inside the terminal.
Most turn out to be false alarms caused by
passengers who intentionally leave luggage or objects
avoid paying overweight or for organic materials
that require special permits for transport.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
The officers intercepted a young passenger who was trying to
travel to Mexico, with a stopover in Panama,
carrying several bags of packaged food that
They were hiding cocaine alkaloid.
AZURIN: Positive for cocaine alkaloid...
NARRATOR: Officers try to get cooperation
of the detainee.
NARRATOR: The detainee remains silent,
But when the agents check their luggage,
Something unexpected happens that convinces him
that collaboration is the only option left.
AZURIN: We found in one of your belongings a small
sample of the child's umbilical cord.
And that somehow sank into him, made him feel some concern.
because of the situation.
NARRATOR: In the presence of the prosecutor,
The officers are waiting for the young man to receive the call.
of the traffickers in order to trace the communication.
All they have to do is wait.
Meanwhile they prepare to gather the drugs to find out the
exact amount the passenger was trying to smuggle
to Mexico.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
And which finally amounts to a total of 2,982 kilograms.
[PHONE RINGING]
Minutes later, the call from the traffickers finally arrives.
who want to know if the passenger has managed to pass the controls
airports.
NARRATOR: Thanks to call tracking,
In the last year it was possible to identify 4 gangs of
drug traffickers operating in Peru.
Before being transferred, the detainee makes the call
He calls his family to inform them of his situation.
NARRATOR: Suspected smuggling attempt
of 2,982 kilograms of cocaine alkaloid,
The young man could receive a sentence of between 8 and 15 years
of prison, which could be reduced if the data
that has contributed helps to find the traffickers.
[SIRENS]
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
LOAYZA: Organizations are definitely looking to bring
the drug in different ways, in luggage,
through objects, for example handcrafted ones.
GUARDAMINO: How many?
KATHERINE: Twenty handmade rugs.
LOAYZA: Unfortunately, the burriers are caught by these
organizations due to the situation they find themselves in.
Above all, they are young people, who sometimes go through difficult times.
economic times.
These young people are actually losing a great project.
life.
ROMERO: They don't realize the world they're entering.
They offer them a certain amount of money,
which is quite appetizing.
AZURIN: How much were you going to get for, for carrying that suitcase?
DETAINED: $3,000. AZURIN: $3,000.
ROMERO: They see what is easy and simply lose their minds.
and consciousness.
ROMERO: We are increasingly trying to strengthen the work
together to better our seizures
and arrests at the airport.
♪ [MUSIC] ♪
[SIRENS] [RADIO VOICES]